<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
    <title>Write, Code, Dream ! | [name, insen][url, https://linkedin.com/nilsengupta]</title>
    <link>http://insen.github.io/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://insen.github.io/blog//rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Personal blog of [name, insen][url, https://linkedin.com/nilsengupta]</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 23:37:02 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 23:37:02 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog like you are coming home.</title>
      <link>http://insen.github.io/blog//2017/08/29/helloblog/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <author> ([name, insen][url, https://linkedin.com/nilsengupta])</author>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://insen.github.io/blog//2017/08/29/helloblog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Hello blog, eh, I mean, world!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far back as I can remember, I have always been writing. However, I have never blogged. Probably because I preferred the diary and the pen. Having caught a lot of flak for it from my friends, well-wishers, colleagues and bosses alike over the years, I finally decided to fix that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, I had conditions -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not much overhead beyond the writing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retain maximum possible control over content, display and offline support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also, I have a technical background so I wanted to learn something out of it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note :&lt;/em&gt; The first and the third above may be self-contradictory, but I am ok with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I started looking. Now, traditional blogging platforms end up keeping my data. I didnt like that.
Plus I havent seen good web-based blog editors. So the web based blogs weren&apos;t options I was inclined to
try first. Having encountered github blogging in the past and liked what I saw, I investigated it again.
Soon, it was clear that the simplicity of a static site was hard to beat. The catch was, Github integrates
Jekyl. Now Jekyll is good, but getting Jekyll on windows involves some fiddling and a good deal of ruby.
Having recently gone through .Net Core, Scala, Spark, Azure and NodeJs recently in quick succession, I had
no appetite for another. A little more looking, and I found &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:8080/#&quot;&gt;Pretzel&lt;/a&gt; - a .NET
based static-site generator, plus extras.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus I settled. &lt;em&gt;(The living-happily-there-ever-after-question has no answers yet.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blogging should be simple. Hence Github pages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blogging i.e. content, display and offline mode should remain in blogger&apos;s control. Hence pretzel and
not jekyll. Also see &lt;a href=&quot;https://thomasfreudenberg.com/archive/2016/05/16/from-jekyll-to-pretzel/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for
more details.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And I get to dig into pretzel and maybe learn about static-site-generators.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oh, and I rather liked the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/poole/hyde&quot;&gt;Jekyll Hugo Theme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, this blog is being served from a Github-pages static site, with the site template taken from
the Jekyll theme called Hyde, actually being generated by Pretzel on local machine and getting checked
into Github.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just need to figure out markdown now, and then technically speaking, I am back to &lt;strong&gt;build, compile,
test and deploy&lt;/strong&gt;. Blog or not, thats like coming home.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel> 
</rss>